(drumroll)
(fanfare playing)
(fanfare ends)
GIRL:
14, 15,
16, prime,
18, prime,
20, 21,
22, prime...
MAN: West Virginia
Collegiate Institute is
the best school
for Negros in the state.
It's the only school
past the eighth grade
anywhere near here.
Isosceles.
Scalene.
Equilateral.
Rhombus.
Trapezoid.
Katherine's
in the sixth grade.
They want to take her early.
KATHERINE:
Tetrahedron.
Dodecahedron.
MAN: They're offering
a full scholarship.
All you have to do is get there.
Ms. Coleman,
why don't you solve
the equation on the board?
WOMAN:
We took up a collection
amongst the teachers and such.
It's not a lot,
but it's enough
to help get you settled in.
That's more than kind,
Ms. Sumner.
If the product
of two terms is zero,
then common sense says
at least one of the two terms
has to be zero to start with.
So if you move all the terms
over to one side,
you can put
the quadratics
into a form
that can be factored,
allowing that side
of the equation
to equal zero.
Once you've done that,
it's pretty straightforward
from there.
SUMNER:
In all my years of teaching,
I've never seen a mind like
the one your daughter has.
-MOTHER: Katherine!
-FATHER: Hurry on now, love!
SUMNER:
You have to go.
Let Mama tuck you in.
SUMNER: You have to see
what she becomes.
(clattering)
WOMAN: Okay,
try to turn it over now.
-(cattle moo)
-Katherine?
Mary!
Somebody!
Katherine!
Quit staring off into space
and turn the damn car over.
I got it.
-I'm not deaf.
-I wonder sometimes.
Here it goes!
(rapid clicking)
Yeah, it's the starter.
That is definitely the starter.
The starter is
starting to make us late.
We all gonna end up
unemployed
riding around in this pile
of junk to work every day.
You're welcome to walk
the 16 miles.
Or sit in the back
of the bus.
(chuckles)
I won't do neither.
I'll hitchhike.
(vehicle approaching)
Girls.
(gasps)
(cattle moo)
No crime
in a broken-down car.
No crime being
Negro neither.
Button it up, Mary.
Nobody wants to go to jail
behind your mouth.
-I'll do my best, sugar.
-(siren blaring)
(siren stops)
(cattle moo)
Not a great place
for three of y'all
be having car trouble.
We didn't pick the place,
Officer. It picked us.
You being disrespectful?
No, sir.
You have identification on you?
-Yes, sir.
We're just on our way
to work at Langley.
NASA, sir.
We do a great deal
of the calculating.
Getting our rockets
into space.
-All three of you?
-Yes, sir.
Yes, Officer.
NASA.
Now that's something.
I had no idea
they hired...
There are quite
a few women
working in the space program.
(cattle moo)
Damn Russians are watching us
right now.
Sputniks.
You girls ever meet
those astronauts?
Mercury Seven?
Absolutely.
Uh, yes, sir. We work with
those gentlemen all the time.
Those boys are
the best we got.
I'm sure of that.
-Yeah.
We gotta get a man up there
before the commies do.
-Yes.
-Absolutely.
Whole damn country's
counting on them.
That's for certain.
MARY:
Hard being of service
broken down on the side
of the road, though.
Right, right. Uh...
Well, do y'all need a tow
or something?
No, thank you, Officer.
I think I got it.
Just give me my...
Just need to bypass
the starter.
She's good at this stuff.
-(engine starts)
-Whoo! Attagirl.
We're all set.
Well, hell, least I can do
is give y'all an escort.
I imagine you're running
late to work.
No, sir. We wouldn't wanna
bother you.
That would be wonderful,
Officer.
Thank you so much, sir.
-Follow me.
-I'm driving.
Hurry up, Dorothy,
before he changes his mind.
-We're coming.
-Hold your horses.
♪ Look at here,
can you move like this? ♪
-(siren wailing)
-♪ It keeps me up ♪
-♪ Anxiety ♪
-♪ Crave ♪
-Whoa, Mary!
-Yes!
Mary, slow down!
You're too close!
Be quiet.
He said to follow him.
He didn't mean
up his behind!
♪ Can't get no sleep
My love is pourin' ♪
Dear Lord, I don't even
know where to begin!
Oh, I'll tell you
where to begin.
Three Negro women are chasing
a white police officer
down the highway
in Hampton, Virginia, 1961.
Ladies, that there is
a God-ordained miracle.
(Dorothy laughing)
And, tomorrow,
I'm riding the bus.
♪ Can somebody help me? ♪
-♪ I'm on the sidewalk ♪
-♪ You got me cravin' ♪
-♪ I'm fallin' over ♪
-♪ Rockin' back and forth ♪
-♪ You got me holdin' my hand ♪
-♪ So help me ♪
-♪ I'm cravin' ♪
-♪ I'm on the sidewalk ♪
-♪ You got me cravin' ♪
-♪ I'm fallin' over ♪
(engine roaring)
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Liftoff is good.
Trajectory is stable.
Show me.
No, exactly.
MAN 2 (over radio):
...three-four-nine-
one-one-zero degrees north.
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Ascent angle 46.56.
Approaching 7,400 miles
per hour.
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
118 seconds.
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Boosters have disengaged.
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Success.
(man speaking
Russian over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Second stage success.
(man speaking Russian
over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Korabl-Sputnik 4 is orbital.
(man speaking Russian
over radio)
MAN 2 (translating over radio):
Orbital entry is established.
-Russian orbital entry
-(telephone ringing)
is established.
(sighs)
Jim Webb.
Yes, Mr. President.
We certainly are, sir.
Uh, it looks like
they've achieved
at least one orbit,
maybe two.
(man speaking Russian)
TRANSLATOR (in English):
Chernushka is ready to go again.
So is our comrade, Ivan,
a brave space traveler.
We have proven life can be
sustained in space.
Now we will be first
to send a human...
WEBB: A damn dog
and a damn mannequin.
And then a one-point-six megaton
RDS-37 thermonuclear warhead
drops down in the middle
of Des Moines.
Well, that's
a pretty big jump, sir.
What?
-Just that... (stammers)
-Who the hell is he?
Paul Stafford, our lead
engineer, Mr. Webb.
I think what
he meant to say
is that speculation,
at least on our side
of the equation,
by definition can be...
just a little dangerous.
Dangerous?
You know what's dangerous,
Mr. Stafford?
Inaction and indecision.
The Russians...
have a spy satellite
lapping the planet,
taking pictures
of God knows what!
The president is demanding
an immediate response.
No more delay.
Alan Shepard, John Glenn,
your Uncle Bob,
it doesn't matter.
Get us up there, Harrison.
We can't justify
a space program
that doesn't put
anything in space.
(murmuring)
How'd that feel
in there, Paul?
You think you enlightened
the administrator?
Hmm?
No, he didn't look
enlightened to me.
He look enlightened
to you, Sam?
-Not particularly.
-And just so you know,
he's not wrong about
what he said in there.
You know that, right?
Because now
that they can get up there,
a bomb will follow.
It's what happens
to all our good ideas.
I imagine theirs too.
Where...
Where's the machine?
Any day now,
Mr. Harrison.
-Any day now.
-Yes, sir.
What's it called?
The initials.
The IBM.
International
Business Machines.
Space as a business.
(scoffs)
I need a mathematician.
I'll put in another
request, sir.
"Another request."
Jesus Christ.
We don't have a single
person in this entire building
that can handle
analytic geometry?
That's what I've been told.
Yeah. Well, tell me
something else, Ruth,
like we're gonna find
such a person
before the Russians
plant a flag
on the damn Moon.
(chattering)
DOROTHY:
All right, Gloria,
you'll be
with engineering, building four.
Ladies, ladies.
If you're tardy, you
don't get an assignment.
If you don't get an assignment,
you don't have a job.
Eleanor.
Data Reduction, building 202.
Data Reduction?
Well, you're welcome
to join the charmers
-in Magnetoplasmadynamics.
-Oh, no, ma'am.
Thank you.
Data Reduction is just fine.
Mm-hmm.
-Mary.
-Present.
The Mercury Seven prototype
has arrived for testing.
Mr. Zielinski's requesting you
for permanent assignment.
-Are you serious?
-Get moving.
Ooh, thank you, Jesus.
Thank you, Jesus!
-Oh, thank you.
-(quietly) Mary, Mary.
Keep it inside.
(whispering)
Okay. I'm sorry, Dor.
DOROTHY:
All right, Miss Late.
You will also be supporting
the East group.
DOROTHY:
Mrs. Mitchell.
We're on double-time
this morning, girls.
I need these calculations
before lunch.
Space Task Group needs
a computer, ASAP.
Someone with a handle
on analytic geometry.
We can't fill that position
out of the East group.
Permanent or temp?
Everything's temporary,
Dorothy.
-You have someone?
-Yes, ma'am.
Katherine's the gal for that.
She can handle any numbers
you put in front of her.
I'll check her credentials.
(muttering)
Didn't think I'd come
all the way down here.
Here. Finish passing those out.
WOMAN:
Yes, ma'am.
Mrs. Mitchell.
If I could?
My application
for supervisor, ma'am.
Was just wondering
if they're still considering
me for that position.
Yes. Well,
the official word is no.
They're not assigning
a permanent supervisor
for the colored group.
-May I ask why?
-I don't know why.
-I didn't ask why.
-We need a supervisor, ma'am.
We haven't had one since
Miss Jansen got sick.
It's been almost a year.
Things are working
just fine as is.
I'm doing the work
of a supervisor.
Well, that's NASA for you.
Fast with rocket ships,
slow with advancement.
Get those trajectory calcs
worked out.
We need them
for the Redstone test.
Mach 1 tunnel test.
T-minus one minute.
(alarm blaring)
(grunts)
No shoe is worth your life.
One--
One moment.
T-minus 10, nine,
eight, seven, six,
five, four...
(alarm continuing outside)
(machines beeping)
(clattering)
Shut it down.
If we alter the exterior
from smooth to corrugated,
the capsule might have
more stability.
But the friction it is
under during reentry...
Most shield erosion occurs
on the posterior side
abutting the retro-boosters.
Conclusion?
The area closest
to the boosters
is closest to the heat.
Coupled with rise
in temperature on reentry,
the contact softens.
We could consider
another fastener
other than the bolts.
Yes.
There is another opening
in the engineer training program.
Flat head rivets
would reduce wind drag.
Mary, a person
with engineer's mind
should be an engineer.
You can't be a computer
the rest of your life.
Mr. Zielinski,
I'm a Negro woman.
I'm not gonna entertain
the impossible.
And I'm a Polish Jew
whose parents died
in a Nazi prison camp.
Now I'm standing
beneath a spaceship
that's going to carry
an astronaut to the stars.
I think we can say
we are living the impossible.
Let me ask you,
if you were a white male,
would you wish to be
an engineer?
I wouldn't have to.
I'd already be one.
MITCHELL: Skirts must be worn
past the knee.
Sweaters are preferred
to blouses.
No jewelry.
A simple pearl necklace
is the exception.
Your supervisor is
Mr. Al Harrison,
director of
the Space Task Group.
You'll write research,
proof calculations, so forth.
Do not talk to Mr. Harrison
unless he talks to you.
Not many computers last
more than a few days.
He's been through a dozen
in as many months.
Come on, keep up.
Things move fast around here.
Your clearance.
They've never had a colored
in here before, Katherine.
Don't embarrass me.
(sighs)
-(indistinct chattering)
-(typewriters clacking)
(telephone ringing)
This wasn't emptied
last night.
I'm sorry, I'm not the...
(quietly)
custodian.
Excuse me, ma'am.
Mr. Harrison's computer
reporting.
Take the desk in the back.
I'll get your work in a... bit.
Mr. Harrison won't warm up
to you. Don't expect it.
Do your work,
keep your head down.
-Thank you.
-Go on. Get settled.
Paul?
Why are we still losing
shingles off the heat shield?
We're working with a prototype
of the capsule, Al.
Its lid is
one-third the size--
I get that. So...
what do we do with
our million-dollar fan, Karl?
-Turn it down?
-No, Al. I don't think--
It was a joke.
Paul, if the heat shield
comes off,
what do you think happens
to our astronaut?
-I know.
-So we're gonna...
We're gonna come up
with a solve, right?
Yes, sir.
We're working on it.
HARRISON: Ruth, what's
the status on that computer?
She's right behind you,
Mr. Harrison.
Does she handle
analytic geometry?
Absolutely.
And she speaks.
Yes, sir. I do.
-Which one?
-Both.
Geometry and speaking.
Ruth, get me the...
You think you, uh...
You think you can find me
the Frenet frame for this data?
-Using the Gram-Schmidt--
-Orthogonalization algorithm.
Yes, sir.
I prefer it
over Euclidean coordinates.
Okay, good.
Good, then I'm gonna need
it by the end of the day.
Yes, sir.
I'm also gonna ask you
to check Mr. Stafford's math
as well as others' on this floor
from time to time.
I can...
I can handle that, Al.
I'm sure you can, Paul.
I'm sure they all can.
But if that were the case,
shingles wouldn't be
flying off the heat shield,
now would they?
Excuse me, could I have
everyone's attention
for a moment?
Thank you.
Just, uh...
Just to be clear,
in 14 days, the Mercury Seven
will be here for training.
And I have no doubt in my mind
that they're going to be
asking us questions
about our work.
I think that's
pretty reasonable given
we're putting a human
on top of a missile,
shooting him into space,
and it's never been
done before.
(laughing)
Because it's never been done,
everything we do between now
and then is gonna matter.
It's gonna matter
to their wives,
to their children.
I believe it's gonna matter
to the whole damn country.
So this Space Task Group
will be as advertised.
America's greatest
engineering and scientific minds
are not gonna have a problem
with having their work checked.
-Are they, Paul?
-No, sir.
Good. So let's have
an amen, damn it.
ALL (mutter):
Amen.
ALL (louder):
Amen!
All right.
(marker squeaking)
My numbers are spot-on.
I will double-check them, sir.
No problem.
Uh...
-I'm not gonna be able--
-Work on what you can read.
The rest is classified.
You don't have clearance.
RUTH: These are the numbers
Mr. Harrison gave me.
-Yes, I'm absolutely--
-Excuse me.
May I ask where
the ladies' room is?
Sorry. I have no idea
where your bathroom is.
Yes, sir.
Uh, yes, sir.
(jazzy melody playing)
♪ Whoo! Mm! ♪
♪ Summertime in Virginia
was an oven ♪
♪ Oven ♪
♪ All the kids eating
ice cream with their cousins ♪
♪ Cousins ♪
♪ I was studyin' while you
was playing the dozens ♪
♪ Dozens ♪
♪ Don't act like you was
there when you wasn't ♪
-♪ Runnin' from the man ♪
-♪ Man ♪
-♪ Runnin' from the badge ♪
-♪ Badge ♪
♪ Don't act like you was
there when you wasn't ♪
-♪ Runnin' toward our plans ♪
-♪ Plans ♪
-♪ And the judge's hands ♪
-♪ Hands ♪
♪ Don't act like you was
there when you wasn't ♪
♪ I know they say
you crawl before you walk ♪
♪ But in my mind
I already jog ♪
♪ If I stand still
I cannot get far ♪
♪ They want the Moon
I'm on Mars ♪
♪ Sometime my mind dives deep
when I'm runnin' ♪
♪ Together we'll fly
Oh, but no more runnin' ♪
♪ Runnin' ♪
-Ruth!
-Yes, Mr. Harrison?
Ruth, where's that girl
with the numbers?
On a... break.
We take breaks now?
-♪ Whoo! ♪
-(panting)
♪ Sometime my mind dives deep
when I'm runnin' ♪
♪ I don't want no free ride ♪
♪ I'm just sick and tired
of runnin' ♪
♪ Together we fly
Oh, but no more runnin' ♪
♪ No ♪
♪ Whoo! ♪
My God,
where have you been?
Are you finished yet?
Uh...
Almost. He said
by the end of the day.
The end of the day around here
is yesterday.
-(banging on glass)
-I need those done first.
He wants
those done first.
-Okay.
-Get going.
HARRISON:
I'm sorry about that.
Somebody's working on it
right now.
(chattering)
KATHERINE:
Mr. Harrison?
Oh, yeah. Uh,
just set it-- you know.
And Stafford's
heat shield calcs?
It's hard
to be sure, sir.
(mutters)
Hard to be sure.
You know
we're doing here?
Trying to put
a man into space, sir.
That's right.
That's right. So you can throw
that in the trash.
Excuse me?
I said you can throw it away.
Here.
It's not an insult
to your work.
It's just obsolete.
That's how fast things are
moving around here.
If I said I was sorry,
I'd be saying it all day.
What I'm asking you to do,
what I'm asking everyone
in that room,
all my geniuses,
is to look beyond the numbers,
to look around them,
through them,
for answers to questions
we don't even know to ask.
Math that doesn't
yet exist.
Because without it,
we're not going anywhere.
I mean, we're staying
on the ground. We're not...
flying into space,
we're not circling the Earth,
and we're certainly not
touching the Moon.
And in my mind...
In my mind,
I'm already there.
Are you?
Yes, sir.
Good.
'Cause I don't need another
smart girl with an adding machine.
Can I go, sir?
(mutters)
Yeah... go...
Yeah, go.
Yes, you can go.
(sighs)
(speaking indistinctly)
DOROTHY:
We've been waiting for hours.
Next time,
you take the bus.
She's in a mood.
(rhythm and blues playing
on car stereo)
♪ People talkin'
tryin' to break us up ♪
♪ Why won't they let us be? ♪
♪ Bricks and stones
may break my bones ♪
♪ But talk don't bother me ♪
♪ I've been abused ♪
♪ In my heart ♪
I haven't been late
one day in 10 years.
Haven't been out sick.
Haven't complained.
My work's on time.
It's done right.
It's done well.
It's not fair,
that's a fact.
What's not fair
is having the responsibility
of a supervisor
-but not the title or the pay.
-MARY: Mmm.
And watching you two move on.
Now, don't get me wrong.
Any upward movement is
movement for us all.
Just isn't movement for me.
Truth be told, Dorothy,
I don't even know
if I can keep up
in that room.
I'll be back
with the computers in a week.
-Or out of a job entirely.
-DOROTHY: Oh, please.
You're better with the numbers
than anyone in there,
Katherine,
and you know it.
Just make that pencil move
as fast as your mind does,
you'll be fine.
And you,
have some respect.
Get your damn feet
off my dashboard.
This isn't
your living room.
I sound like
a supervisor, don't I?
A mean old salty one.
Riddled with authority,
no question.
(laughs)
You don't mess
with Mrs. Vaughan.
Turn that music up.
♪ They'll say anything
just to make me feel bad ♪
♪ Yes, anything
to make me shame ♪
-♪ Yes, I know ♪
-♪ Ah, yes, I know ♪
-♪ Yes, I do ♪
♪ Oh, don't you know
it's true, yeah ♪
-DOROTHY: Good night, Katherine.
-MARY: Bye, Kat.
Good night, ladies.
See you in the morning.
(slow jazz music playing softly)
-Hey, baby.
-Hello, Mama.
I was fixing to call
the National Guard.
Sorry, Mama.
New assignment.
Space Task Group.
Oh, my word.
That sounds important.
It's a promotion?
(chuckles)
It might be
a slight promotion.
But you want the job, right?
I think so.
It's a challenge, but...
Well, it's nothing
you can't handle, Katherine.
-Thank you, Mama.
-(chuckles)
-Are they asleep yet?
-They're pretending to be.
(children arguing)
They're not pretending
well enough.
-GIRL: Constance!
-Thank you, Mama. Love you.
-This is my bed.
-No. Get off!
-Go back to yours! I'm oldest!
-No.
Get off!
What are you doing?
It's not fair how Joylette
gets to sleep by herself
because she's the oldest.
-Yes, it is fair.
-No, it's not.
-Nuh-uh.
Constance, Kathy, sit.
Now, I understand
you want to be grown
and have your own space.
So, whoever sleeps in that bed,
in Joylette's place,
will also do the dishes,
take out the trash,
and do all
of Joylette's chores.
That's okay.
Never mind.
Yeah, she's not so terrible
to share with.
(chuckles)
Okay. Then don't let me
come home
and find you like this again,
you hear me?
You're supposed to been
asleep a long time ago.
We just wanted to say
good night.
You've been gone
for 300 hours.
I know. I work
a full-time job now.
You all know that.
I have to be Mommy and Daddy.
I miss your father
just as much as anyone.
He's with the angels.
Yes, he's with
all the angels.
And he's watching over us.
Every minute, okay?
That's why
we have to be strong.
All right?
-Yes, Mama.
Y'all get some rest, okay?
-Mama?
-Yes, baby?
Are the Russians fixin'
to attack us?
Where'd you get that from?
We had to hide
under our desks today,
all scrunched up.
Okay, baby,
that's called a drill.
It means, uh...
you practice safety
just in case
something happens.
Truth is, we don't know
what they're doing up there.
-You going to space, too?
-No, baby.
But I'm going to do
what I can
to help those brave men
get there. Yes, I am.
You could fly up to space
if you wanted to, Mama.
You could be an astronaut.
-Did you draw this?
-Yes, Mama.
(laughs)
Is that me?
Mmm-hmm.
You see this?
Oh, my goodness.
I love you, baby.
I know. I know.
Come here.
All right. Now this time
really go to bed.
(kisses) Okay?
-I love y'all.
-Good night.
-Good night, Mama.
I love my picture, baby.
(choir singing)
Thank you, Lord.
-Praise God!
-Hallelujah!
-Hallelujah.
-(murmurs of approval)
-Praise God...
-Praise God.
...that change is coming.
(murmurs of approval)
From the Southern Christian
Leadership Conference
to the good Reverend Dr. King...
-Amen!
-Hallelujah!
...to the students sitting in
at lunch counters
in North Carolina.
-That's right.
-Yes, sir.
His faith in us has no limit.
The good Lord
has our very own women
working on rocket ships!
(applause)
And we have National Guardsmen
defending our freedom.
Give a shout of praise
for Colonel Jim Johnson.
(applause)
Returning home,
by the grace of God
to set up a National Guard unit
right here in Hampton.
Can I get
a hallelujah in here?
Hallelujah!
(church bell ringing)
I just don't understand.
I just... I don't--
I don't understand it.
I don't wanna talk
about this again, okay?
But a female engineer?
A female engineer?
We're Negro, baby.
Ain't no such thing.
Understand it.
It's not like
that there, Levi.
You can't apply for freedom.
Freedom is never granted
to the oppressed.
It's got to be demanded, taken.
Stop quoting
your slogans at me.
There is more than one way
to achieve something.
I don't want any greens.
Hey. I tell you about
interrupting?
Here. Try this, baby.
Yes.
You're gonna eat
them greens, too.
Kids need to eat
their vegetables.
You'd know that
if you was ever home.
You better settle down,
Levi Jackson.
Unless you want
this female's mind,
right here,
in front of everybody.
(quietly) Alls I'm saying,
don't play the fool.
I don't wanna see
you get hurt.
NASA's never, ever given
you gals your due.
Having a couple of extra degrees
ain't gonna change that.
Civil rights ain't
always civil.
I don't want
any greens either.
No lip, little miss.
Your brother gets them,
and so do you.
I hear he's planning on
staying in the area.
Well...
Well, that's good for him.
Katherine, go find
your way over there.
That Colonel Jim is
a tall glass of water.
That he is.
-Tall, strong, commanding.
-Oh...
And I bet he's like that
day and night.
-Mary, it's Sunday.
-(scoffs)
-Please have some shame.
-I will not.
Hmm, I think
he's smiling over here.
At you.
Well, I'm not smiling back.
-Yes, you are.
-Oh, child.
-You are all teeth right now.
-I am not.
(mouthing) Come over
here and say hi.
DOROTHY:
He's coming over.
KATHERINE: Now, why would
he be doing that?
-'Cause Mary's waving at him.
-No!
-Ladies, I'm not ready.
-It's too late. Fix your hair.
Hello, Colonel.
I'm Dorothy Vaughan.
That's Mary Jackson.
I believe you met
her husband, Levi.
Yes, ma'am.
Good to meet y'all.
And Mrs. Katherine Goble.
She's not married.
She's a widow,
with three
beautiful little girls.
So well behaved.
Angels on Earth is
what we like to call them.
Dorothy,
slice of pie?
I'd love one.
Excuse me.
-You already have a slice of pie, Dorth--
-Uh-huh.
Well, I was just, uh, fixing
my three babies some plates.
-Let me help you.
-Sure.
Uh, fruit salad.
Mmm-hmm.
Pastor mentioned
you're a computer at NASA.
-Yes.
-What's that entail?
Um... we calculate
the mathematics necessary
to enable launch and landing
for the space program.
(laughing) That's
pretty heady stuff.
Yes, it is.
They let women handle
that sort of... (stammers)
That's...
not what I mean.
What do you mean?
Well...
I'm just surprised
that something so...
-taxing.
-Hmm.
Mr. Johnson.
If I were you,
I'd quit talking right now.
I didn't mean
no disrespect.
I will have you know,
I was the first
Negro female student
at West Virginia University
Graduate School.
On any given day,
I analyze the manometer levels
for air displacement,
friction, and velocity,
and compute
over 10,000 calculations
by cosine, square root,
and, lately, analytic geometry.
By hand.
There are 20 bright,
highly capable
Negro women
in the West Computing Group,
and we're proud to be doing
our part for the country.
So, yes.
They let women do some things
at NASA, Mr. Johnson.
And it's not because
we wear skirts.
It's because
we wear glasses.
Have a good day.
-(band playing patriotic march)
-(applauding)
Scott, welcome to Langley.
-Welcome to Langley.
-Welcome.
HARRISON: Good to have you here,
gentlemen.
(cheering, whistling)
Thank you.
That's Alan Shepard,
US Navy pilot.
He could be
the first man in space.
And that's Scott Carpenter
and Walter Schirra,
also Navy pilots.
All under 5' 11", 180 pounds.
-IQs over 130.
-Mmm.
And handsome must be
a requirement too.
How could you possibly
be ogling these white men?
It's equal rights.
I have the right to see
fine in every color.
DOROTHY:
And that's John Glenn.
He's the only
Marine Corps pilot.
Gentlemen, if we may,
much to see around here.
Well, heck, we haven't
shaken all the hands yet.
We have a fairly tight
itinerary, Colonel.
-Ruth, he's fine.
-He's coming this way.
-KATHERINE: Look straight ahead.
-MARY: Look right him.
Ladies, I didn't wanna run
off without saying hello.
They seem to be
in a big rush around here.
Well, the Russians certainly
aren't slowing down any.
You know, they can't build
a damn refrigerator.
How the heck did
they beat us into space?
(all laughing)
GLENN: And what do you ladies
do for NASA?
Calculate your trajectories.
Launch and landing.
You can't get anywhere
without the numbers.
No, sir.
Mary Jackson, Mr. Glenn.
Engineering.
And I'm proud as the devil
to be working with you.
Thank you, Mary.
John.
-John, let's take it inside.
-Yes, sir.
-Guys.
-Nice meeting you guys.
-Thank you, Colonel.
-Good luck, sir.
God bless you all.
Thank you.
Wonderful.
Thank you!
-(phones ringing)
-(chattering)
Mr. Harrison wants
you to confirm
launch and landing
for the Redstone rocket test.
I cannot work on
what I cannot see, Mr. Stafford.
It's illegible.
Those numbers have
already been confirmed
by two engineers in this
department and myself.
This is more or less
a dummy check.
We have one, you make it two.
Make it double, okay?
You gotta get it--
Just make it happen.
No one thought
to measure these things?
I'm afraid not, sir.
Well, would you
like us to stop?
No. No, no, just...
Actually, no.
Just keep going.
In fact,
use the big hammer.
Yes, sir.
Come on, use the big hammer.
You heard the man. Let's go. Go.
(phone ringing)
Ma'am.
Our runner can pick up
your work, Dorothy.
You need to be working,
not walking.
Oh. It's break time, ma'am.
No trouble at all.
Well, since you
made the trip,
you can take that batch
over there.
Sure thing, Mrs. Mitchell.
-You need something else?
-Yes, ma'am. Um...
I was wondering if you know
what they're building
over in the tech wing.
It's called an IBM.
A mainframe machine.
Apparently, it can do
our calculations
in a fraction of the time.
Hmm.
I guess that's good for NASA.
Hurry on, now.
Best if you do it in one trip.
(grunts)
Excuse me.
Hi.
What are you
looking at, Paul?
Is that correct?
Yeah.
Whose work is that?
I said,
whose work is that?
Katherine Goble, sir.
-Hello.
-Hi.
PAUL:
How did you know the Redstone
couldn't support orbital flight?
-That's classified information.
-It's top secret.
Well, it's no secret why
the Redstone tests keep failing.
It's fine
for suborbital flight,
but it can't handle
the weight of the capsule
and push it into space.
Numbers don't lie.
And you figured
all that out with this?
Half the data is redacted.
Well, what's there tells a story
if you read between the lines.
The distance from
launch to orbit, we know.
Redstone mass, we know.
Mercury capsule weight,
we know.
And the speeds are
there in the data.
-You did the math.
-Yes, sir.
I looked beyond.
And how do you know
about the Atlas rocket?
That's not math.
That data is not here.
Like he said, it's classified.
I held it up to the light.
You held it
up to the light?
Yes, sir.
-Well, there it is.
-KATHERINE: Mmm-hmm.
Atlas.
-What's your name?
-Katherine Goble.
-Are you a spy, Katherine?
-Am I what?
I said, are you
a Russian spy?
No, sir.
I'm not Russian.
She's not
Russian, sir.
All right then, we have
nothing to lose here.
Give her everything she needs
to work on Shepard's
trajectories without redaction.
-Are we clear on that?
-Are we sure about this?
What's the issue, Paul?
You heard her.
She's not a spy.
I-- I just don't think
it's a good idea.
You know what I think's
a good idea? Darker ink.
I think darker ink's
a good idea.
-Ruth, could you pass it along?
-Yes, sir.
-Thank you, Katherine.
-Thank you, sir.
(sighs)
This interrogation's over.
(chatting)
MARY: You can probably
get to the Moon
and back with this.
Just not the bathroom.
Well, at least they're
not blind of what you do.
It's not gonna
matter soon.
This IBM's gonna
put us all out of work.
How you doing?
What can we do about it?
-How you doing?
-Only one thing to do.
Learn all we can,
make ourselves valuable.
Somewhere down the line,
a human being
is gonna have to push
the buttons.
That's right.
Oh, mercy.
MARY:
Well, she must be lost.
NASA doesn't
commission females
for the engineer
training program.
That position is available
to any qualified applicant.
Right. Except, you don't have
the educational requirements.
I have a bachelor's degree
in mathematics
and physical science.
It's the same as most
engineers around here.
Well, we now require
advanced extension courses
through
the University of Virginia.
It's in the employee handbook,
in addendum.
In case you haven't read it.
Every time we have
a chance to get ahead,
they move the finish line.
I just follow
the rules around here,
and I expect everyone
who works for me
to follow them as well.
There are no special
circumstances for anyone.
Y'all should be thankful
you have jobs at all.
"For those that cannot
attend classes
"at the University of Virginia,
"advanced extension courses
are available
at the Hampton
High School."
That's still a segregated
school, Mary.
Virginia acts like Brown
versus Board of Education
never happened.
They are never gonna allow
a colored woman
to just take classes
at an all-white school.
Well, sounds
about right.
That's all you gonna say?
Well, I'm not gonna sit here
all day and listen to you
complain about
the way things are.
We're trying to play cards.
Petition the court.
Fight for what you want.
But quit talking about it.
-I've been complaining?
-For days.
Ladies...
not one more peep about work.
-Deal me in.
-Katherine?
-MARY: Come on.
-KATHERINE: Oh, no.
-MARY: Right here.
-You.
-Child, I needed this.
-(blues music playing)
Thank you.
-(whoops)
-(laughs)
Don't give her
anymore, Katherine.
-I can't. She drank it all.
-(chuckles)
Listen, I'm fine.
I'm as fine
as I have ever been.
You're drunk
as you've ever been.
(laughs)
Come on.
Let's dance, ladies.
Come on, Kat.
Let's dance.
Go and dance with her,
Katherine.
Come on.
-Get out here.
-Hide that.
-We gonna teach you how to dance.
-You go ahead.
All right. Slow.
We gonna teach you
how to get a man.
-Teach me what?
-Come on!
You got to know how to dance.
-Slow. Slow.
-Come on.
-Twirl it around.
-Twirl, twirl.
-Yes!
-Twirl, twirl, twirl.
Whoo! Look at her, Dorothy.
Can I win me one of those
fancy dance contests?
Whip it around.
(laughing)
-Yeah, and on the outside.
-(people chanting)
Was it better than Mama's?
-No, not really.
-Segregation must go!
CROWD (chanting):
Segregation must go!
-Segregation must go!
-(barking)
Segregation must go!
Don't pay attention
to all that.
We're not part
of that trouble. Go on.
Segregation must go!
"Mind.
They must have done..."
(continues indistinctly)
We don't want
any trouble in here.
Oh, I'm not here
for any trouble, ma'am.
-What are you here for?
-A book.
You have books
in the colored section.
It doesn't have
what I'm looking for.
Well, that's
just the way it is.
Go on, now.
You know better than this.
Get your hands off my boys!
Don't touch them.
You have a blessed day.
DOROTHY:
Separate and equal
are two different things.
Just 'cause it's the way,
doesn't make it right.
-Understand?
-Yes, Mama.
You act right,
you are right.
That's for certain.
-Understand?
-Yes, Mama.
You took
that book, Mama?
Son, I pay taxes.
And taxes pay
for everything in that library.
You can't take something
you already paid for.
"Fortran is a new
and exciting language
"used by programmers
to communicate with computers.
It is exciting as it is
the wave of the future."
-All right, everybody smile.
-Aw!
(cheers, laughter)
-Make a wish.
-Blow.
KATHERINE: Try again.
There you go.
Leonard, you need
to get you a job now.
-Mm-hmm.
-Two jobs.
-Your baby is nine...
-Thank you, man.
Yeah, you're
just in time.
Well, look at that.
-Look at what?
-What a surprise.
Can't complain, man.
It's been working out well.
-I'll say.
-(scoffs)
-Howard must have invited him.
-Mmm-hmm.
Let me go help him
with those flowers.
(rhythm and blues playing)
♪ A mighty good loving, baby ♪
♪ Is gonna change
the way you act ♪
WOMAN: Walter,
you behave yourself.
♪ And make you feel so fine ♪
♪ And that's a natural fact ♪
WOMAN: That's right, baby.
Shake it.
♪ When I get you
by your hand ♪
♪ You're gonna let me
have your heart ♪
-Good to see you.
-You too. Thank you.
♪ There'll be
nothing you can do ♪
♪ Oh, when mighty good loving
gets a hold on you ♪
♪ It's mighty good ♪
I believe I owe you
an apology.
-Well, was that it?
-(chuckles)
Can I make it
while we dance?
♪ It's so good now,
it's so good ♪
♪ Little girl, it's true
there'll be nothing you can do ♪
♪ Oh, when mighty good loving
gets a hold on you ♪
I'm afraid I simply misspoke
the other day, Mrs. Goble.
(slow ballad playing)
I've been away
for a long time.
I imagine
I'm just out of practice.
Mmm-hmm.
I was hoping you'd allow me
to start over.
Mmm-hmm.
See, the thing is,
I have an interest
in getting to know you better.
-Mmm-hmm.
-(chuckles)
You're one tough
customer, huh?
(laughing)
You haven't said
you're sorry yet.
Right.
Of course.
I'm sorry, Katherine.
For what, Jim?
For underestimating you.
-Mm.
And any other
woman like you.
Though I don't imagine
there's many.
That's good practice,
right there.
(radio beeping)
MAN (over radio):
We interrupt this musical
programming with breaking news.
The Soviet news agency
has announced
that Russian cosmonaut,
Yuri Gagarin,
has become
the first man in space.
Gagarin completed
one full orbit
around the planet
in 108 minutes.
Stay tuned to this station
for more details
as they become available.
Well, guess that puts us
behind the curve.
ANNOUNCER:
The Vostok-1 rocket delivered
Russian cosmonaut
Yuri Gagarin's 3KA capsule
into orbit at 6:07 UTC,
reentering Russian airspace
at 7:55 UTC,
proving conclusively
that man could survive
orbital space flight.
Gagarin was awarded
the Order of Lenin
and the Gold Star--
Well, they beat
the pants off us. Let's go.
Let's learn
how to fly to space.
ANNOUNCER:
"First Soviet Astronaut,"
and has been proclaimed
a national hero.
This is a day
of unprecedented triumph
for the Russian space program
and a crushing blow for America
in the race for space.
I want to thank everyone
for staying.
I know it's late,
and after what I just saw,
I'm sure everyone's probably
anxious to just go home.
Before we do,
I just have to ask a question...
the same one I've
been asking myself
all the way over here,
which is...
How in the hell did we find
ourself in second place
in a two-man race?
Anybody?
Paul?
And I think
Glenn said it pretty well.
They're just outworking us.
The reason I have to think that
is because I refuse to believe
that the Russians
are smarter than us
or that they have
more technology
or that they care more.
But I don't know.
Is that possible?
Is it possible that it actually
means more to them?
We're in the fight
of our lives, people.
We're not on
some epic joyride.
I just saw seven faces
who aren't sure
that we can get there.
This is our problem.
And so as of right now...
there's only two things you
need to know going forward.
One is staying here,
working late,
that's gonna be
a fact of life.
And two, don't expect
your paychecks
to reflect the extra time
it's gonna take
to catch up
and pass those bastards.
For those of you
who can't work that way,
I understand and thank you
for what you've done.
For everyone else...
I suggest you call your wives
and tell them
how it's gonna be.
I'll start with mine.
(murmuring)
(murmuring continuing)
(up-tempo jazz music playing)
Sam, turn it up.
Turn it up.
Yes, sir.
-John.
-Morning, sir.
(whirring)
(speaking indistinctly)
End of the day.
Okay, we're looking good.
Okay.
(sighs)
Sir, it might be
the selector latch.
I'm taking a walk.
We're honored to serve
our country.
So we don't think
about danger.
We don't have time
to be scared.
We got a job to do.
-Good morning.
WOMAN:
Mrs. Jackson.
Colored seats are
at the back of the courtroom.
Thank you, ma'am.
So, which one of you
wants to go first?
(laughing)
(applauding)
The IBM 7090
Data Processing System.
It has the capability
of solving
over 24,000 multiplications...
per second.
Holy Moses,
that's lightning fast.
They'll never get that to work.
(chuckles)
Oh, it'll run eventually.
And when it does, we have to
know how to program it.
Unless you'd rather
be out of a job.
ALL:
No, ma'am.
Mr. Z!
I got a court date.
"The computer uses it
"as its high-speed
storage unit,
an information-holding device."
Hmm.
So you have a brain.
That I can work with.
Well, that's in the wrong spot.
Attagirl.
-HARRISON: Ruth.
-Yes, sir.
Get me the Cape on the line.
Shepard's trajectories
need to be updated.
Wow.
Where is she?
(jazzy melody playing)
♪ You and I are no different
from each other ♪
♪ Shut our eyes when
we slumber I see numbers ♪
♪ Black and white we're
computers, I am color ♪
♪ Don't act like you was
there when you wasn't ♪
(toilet flushes)
♪ I don't want no free ride ♪
♪ I'm just sick and tired
of runnin' ♪
♪ Some nights I cry ♪
♪ 'Cause I can see
the day comin' ♪
♪ Together we fly
Oh, but no more runnin' ♪
♪ Runnin' ♪
♪ No more runnin' ♪
-(thunder rumbling)
-(panting)
♪ No more runnin' ♪
Where the hell have you been?
Everywhere I look, you're
not where I need you to be.
It's not my imagination.
Now where the hell
do you go every day?
To the bathroom, sir.
To the bathroom?
To the damn bathroom.
For 40 minutes a day?
What do you do
in there?
We're T-minus zero here.
I put a lot of faith in you.
There's no bathroom
for me here.
What do you mean there's
no bathroom for you here?
There is no bathroom.
There are no colored bathrooms
in this building
or any building outside
the West Campus,
which is half a mile away.
Did you know that?
I have to walk to Timbuktu
just to relieve myself.
And I can't use
one of the handy bikes.
Picture that, Mr. Harrison.
My uniform--
skirt below my knees, my heels,
and a simple string of pearls.
Well, I don't own pearls.
Lord knows you don't pay
coloreds enough to afford pearls!
And I work like a dog,
day and night,
living off of coffee from a pot
none of you wanna touch!
(Katherine's breath trembling)
(inhales deeply)
(softly) So, excuse me
if I have to go to the restroom
a few times a day.
(metal clanging)
(grunts)
There we have it.
No more colored restrooms.
No more white restrooms.
-Just plain old toilets.
-(crowbar clangs)
Go wherever
you damn well please.
Preferably closer to your desk.
Here at NASA,
we all pee the same color.
(knocking on door)
(coughing)
Heard you was fighting
the flu.
Figured you could use
some soup.
Hot meal for the girls.
Come on in. (chuckles)
(clears throat)
Excuse me.
Okay, ladies.
Let's say grace.
Bow your heads.
Dear Lord,
thank you for this meal.
We ask that you bless this food
so that it may bless our bodies.
In Jesus's name we pray.
-Amen.
REPORTER: It's a historic day,
here at Cape Canaveral,
and here's
what we can expect.
Alan Shepard and Freedom 7
will be launched into space
at an altitude
of about 116 miles an hour.
Dorothy, come on,
you gonna miss it!
DOROTHY:
I'm coming.
...will land about 35 miles
off the coast of Florida
where he'll be picked up
by the men of
the USS Lake Champlain
who set out
for this historic purpose.
MAN (over radio): Freedom 7,
we're gonna have to bleed off
some of the pressure
inside the liquid oxygen tank.
That should reduce the temperature
inside the capsule. Over.
Any day now, CAPCOM.
SHEPARD (over radio): Fix your little
problem and light this candle.
Roger that, Freedom 7.
Stand by.
Temperature is returning
to normal.
Running one more
launch status check.
All systems now go.
Move to final
countdown sequence.
Moving to final
SHEPARD (over radio):
Roger that.
We're at T-minus 10,
nine,
eight,
seven,
six,
five,
four,
three,
two,
one,
zero.
(roaring)
We have ignition.
And we have liftoff.
Get up there.
SHEPARD: Liftoff,
and the clock is started.
(rattling)
(over radio): Fuel is go.
Two-point-five g.
Get on up there.
Liftoff at 34 minutes
after the hour.
(roaring)
(rattling)
Pitch 88. Trajectory is good.
Yaw is okay.
Switching manual roll.
-Yes!
-(cheering)
JOHN F. KENNEDY:
For the eyes of the world
now look into space,
to the Moon and
to the planets beyond.
-Yes!
-And we have vowed
that we shall not see it
governed
by a hostile flag of conquest
but by a banner of freedom
and peace.
We set sail on this new sea
because there is
new knowledge to be gained
and new rights to be won.
We choose to go to the Moon
in this decade
and do the other things,
not because they are easy,
but because they are hard.
Suppose we should all thank
President Kennedy
for the continued job security.
(snapping)
Uh, Gus Grissom's up next.
Another suborbital flight
with a Redstone.
It's our last shot before
we strap Glenn to the Atlas
and pray we can bring
him back down.
Yes, and I imagine
he'd like us
to have the math worked out
beforehand.
(laughter)
Good work, gentlemen.
Go have dinner with your kids
and let's get back to work.
♪ Look what
you've done to me ♪
♪ Look what you've
done to me ♪
♪ You make me behave
like I wouldn't ever ♪
♪ I know you're
the one for me ♪
♪ You're the one for me ♪
♪ Your essence is the ink
in the word "forever" ♪
I think it's high time
I kissed you, Katherine.
Oh. And why is that?
Figured you attracted to me,
same as I to you.
-Is that right?
-Mmm-hmm.
Or you would have told me
to get going a long time ago.
(laughing)
Haven't kissed a man
in a long time.
Almost forgot how to.
REPORTER (over TV):
The FBI has arrested
four white men
accused of throwing a firebomb
into a Freedom Rider bus
outside of Anniston, Alabama.
-Hi, baby.
-Hi, Mama.
MAN (on TV):
We all hit the floor.
All of us realized
that the bus was on fire
and had to go out
into the mob.
The kids don't need
-to be watching this.
-They need to see this.
Well, when we got off
the bus in Birmingham...
LEVI:
Everybody needs to see this.
...took me and forced me
out of the door...
and threw me into the crowd.
And then I was beaten
by one big guy and several others.
We think we're rendering
a great service to our nation.
For this is not a struggle
for ourselves alone.
It is a struggle to save
the soul of America.
WOMAN:
Mary Jackson.
Petition to attend courses
at Hampton High School
Good morning, Your Honor.
Hampton High School is
a white school, Mrs. Jackson.
Yes, Your Honor.
I'm aware of that.
Virginia,
still a segregated state.
Regardless of what
the federal government says,
regardless of what
the Supreme Court says,
our law is the law.
Your Honor, if I may.
I believe there are special
circumstances to be considered.
What would warrant
a colored woman
attending a white school?
May I approach your bench, sir?
Your Honor, you of all people
should understand
the importance of being first.
How's that, Mrs. Jackson?
Well, you were the first
in your family
to serve in the armed forces.
US Navy.
The first to attend university.
George Mason.
And the first state judge
to be recommissioned
by three
consecutive governors.
You've done some research.
Yes, sir.
What's the point?
The point is, Your Honor,
no Negro woman
in the state of Virginia
has ever attended
an all-white high school.
It's unheard of.
Yes. Unheard of.
And before Alan Shepard sat
on top of a rocket,
no other American
had ever touched space.
And now, he will forever
be remembered
as the US Navy man
from New Hampshire,
the first to touch the stars.
And I, sir,
I plan on being
an engineer at NASA,
but I can't do that
without taking them classes
at that all-white high school.
And I can't change
the color of my skin.
So I have no choice
but to be the first.
Which I can't do
without you, sir.
Your Honor, out of all the cases
you're gonna hear today,
which one is gonna matter
a hundred years from now?
Which one is gonna
make you the first?
(chuckles, mutters)
I'll be darned.
Only the night classes,
Mrs. Jackson.
(yells)
Yes, yes, yes!
Yes!
Oh, my God.
I cannot believe.
How late did he say
he was gonna be?
-KATHERINE: Excuse me.
-No more than five minutes, sir.
Gus Grissom's
coordinates.
I'd like to get a jump
on John Glenn's trajectory.
Do you have any idea
what you're asking?
An orbital launch
with an Atlas rocket
is going to take time.
Is there a problem?
Mr. Harrison...
I was wondering.
Uh-huh. Well,
I've been wondering
my whole life,
so you just spit it out.
Well, sir...
I would like to get a jump
on John Glenn's trajectory.
This isn't about
plugging in numbers.
It's about
inventing the math.
And I think you and I talked
about that, right?
-It doesn't exist.
-I can do it, sir.
PAUL:
Do you have any idea how
exacting these calculations
have to be?
It's like shooting
a sawed-off shotgun
from a thousand feet
and getting that one BB
through a hole so tiny,
you can't even see it.
-Okay, let me see what you've got.
-I'm an excellent shot, sir.
How have the Grissom
numbers been?
They've been spot-on.
Give Glenn's orbit a go.
But you run it all through
-Stafford, understood?
-Yes, sir.
Thank you.
Computers
don't author reports.
GRISSOM: (over radio) CAPCOM,
this is Liberty Bell 7.
CAPCOM:
Loud and clear.
Okay, it's a nice ride
up to now.
CAPCOM:
Roger.
Liberty Bell 7, this is
Hunt 1 approaching.
Ready to hook on. Over.
GRISSOM: I read you
loud and clear. Over.
The hatch is blown, CAPCOM.
TV REPORTER:
The Liberty Bell 7 capsule
is taking on water.
Gus Grissom is
out of the capsule.
Rescuers are
now going to pull him
from the ocean waves.
Unfortunately,
the Liberty Bell 7 capsule...
is lost.
Mama.
-I can't, I can't.
-Mary.
MAN:
Mr. Harrison, taxpayer money
sank in the ocean
along with your capsule.
So what makes you think
you can bring John Glenn
home safely?
Let me say first,
discovery is never
just for the sake
of discovery, gentlemen,
but for the sake
of human survival,
and it will always come
with a risk.
Whoever gets there first
will make the rules,
that's been true
of every civilization.
And so...
I think the bigger question
for this body to consider is
who do you want calling
the shots in space?
We have to know
what's out there, Senator.
We have to touch the stars,
if only to ensure our
own survival,
and only a man can do that.
We'll get John Glenn home
safely because we have to,
because he has to tell us
what he saw.
PAUL: The Redstone rocket
went straight up.
But the capsule didn't have
enough speed
to go into orbit,
so it came back down.
Essentially a triangle:
Earth, suborbit, Earth.
That math was known.
That took Shepard,
took Grissom.
That cannot take Glenn.
Now, the Atlas rocket...
that can push us into orbit.
Goes up, delivers the capsule
into an elliptical orbit.
Earth's gravity keeps
pulling at it,
but it's going so fast,
it keeps missing the Earth.
That's how it stays in orbit.
Now, getting it back down...
that's the math we don't know.
Yes, Katherine.
So the capsule will spin around
the Earth forever
because there's nothing
to slow it down?
That's right.
Slowing it down at precisely
the right moment,
at precisely the right amount,
that's the task.
Yes, Katherine.
So it needs to move
from an elliptical orbit...
to a parabolic orbit.
Yes.
That's the go-no-go.
Now at this point,
it's a pinhead.
-We bring him in too soon...
-He burns up on reentry.
That's right.
We bring him in too late,
he's pushed out
of Earth's gravity.
And any changes to mass,
weight, speed, time,
distance, friction,
or a puff of wind
would alter the go-no-go,
and we start
our calculations over.
Yes.
So we need to be able
to choose this reentry point.
Now this go-no-go,
this has to be exact.
Sam.
These are the latest
Redstone numbers
in current capsule data.
-Obviously, we know the launch spot.
-Thanks.
A Pentagon briefing
should illuminate
where the Navy needs
the recovery zone,
then we work backwards
from there.
And the rest is on us,
so let's get to work.
-Uh... Mr. Stafford.
-What, Katherine?
If I could attend
the briefings,
I'd be more useful
to the project.
Pentagon briefings are
closed-door.
Yes, but if we don't have
the information
of the changes,
we can't keep up.
I need those changes
as they occur.
As you said,
it's a pinhead.
Katherine,
that's the job.
You asked
for this assignment,
so just calculate
with what you have.
Or we'll find
someone who can.
(sighs)
Okay.
Attagirl. (chuckles)
Hey, what the hell are you doing?
You can't be in here.
Who are you?
I'm with
the West Computing Group.
Dorothy Vaughan, sir.
Well, this is a very delicate
piece of equipment.
I'm sorry, sir.
I'm just trying to be helpful.
-Uh-huh.
-Bill, we've got numbers.
What kind of numbers?
Well, I'll be.
What's your name again?
Dorothy Vaughan.
Sir, the parameters
for Friendship 7.
Oh, this is all moot.
We're altering the window
on the capsule.
-When did this happen?
-Six minutes ago.
The math is changing.
Start over.
Sir, if I could attend the briefings,
I could stay current--
Katherine,
we have been through this.
It is not possible.
There is no protocol
for women attending.
There's no protocol for a man circling
the Earth either, sir.
Okay. That is just
the way things are.
-(voices murmuring)
-(phone ringing)
Colonel Glenn's
launch coordinates,
accounting for
the window change, sir.
I have told you this.
Computers don't author
reports. Fix it.
Those are my calculations.
My name should be on it.
That is not the way
this works.
Paul. What's
happening here?
Mr. Harrison, I would like
to attend today's briefing.
And why is that?
Well, sir, the data changes
so fast, the capsule changes.
The weight and the landing zones
are all changing, every day.
I do my work,
you attend these briefings,
I have to start over.
Colonel Glenn launches
in a few weeks.
We don't have the math
figured out yet.
Why is it she can't attend?
Because she doesn't
have clearance, Al.
I cannot do my work effectively
if I do not have all of the data
and all of the information
as soon as it's available.
I need to be in that room,
hearing what you hear.
Pentagon briefings
are not for civilians.
It requires
the highest clearance.
I feel like I'm the best person
to present my calculations--
-You're not gonna let this go, are you?
-No, I am not.
And she is a woman.
There is no protocol for a woman
attending these meetings.
Okay, I get that part, Paul.
But within these walls,
who, uh, who makes the rules?
You, sir.
You are the boss.
You just have to act
like one. Sir.
You keep quiet.
Thank you.
Good morning.
Gentlemen.
(chattering)
(chattering stops)
This is Katherine Goble
with our Trajectory
and Launch Window Division.
Her work is pertinent
to today's proceedings.
Come on.
Want to get her a chair?
We have a confirmed
launch window--
-Get her a chair, please.
-Yes, sir.
We have a confirmed launch
window for Friendship 7.
Let's discuss a landing zone.
The Navy needs
a singular landing zone.
Twenty miles square is
what we can service for retrieval.
Outside of that, we risk
the capsule's recovery.
We'd like three possible
recovery areas.
We can't cover
half the damn ocean.
With all due respect,
our capsule's being altered daily.
We're orbiting the Earth
at what speed now?
Uh...
17,544 miles per hour,
at the time the rocket
delivers the capsule
into low space orbit.
Well, that's one hell
of a speeding ticket.
(laughter)
Okay. So we have
the vehicle's speed,
the launch window,
and for argument's sake,
the landing zone
is the Bahamas.
Should be enough
to figure the go-no-go?
Yeah, in theory, sir.
We need to be past theory
at this point.
We'll be able to calculate
a go-no-go with that information.
When exactly is
that gonna happen?
(chuckles)
Katherine.
Have a go at it.
(clears throat)
(inhales deeply)
(exhales)
The go point for
reentry is 2,990 miles...
from where we want
Colonel Glenn to land.
If we assume
that's the Bahamas,
at 17,544 miles per hour,
upon reentry,
370 feet,
at a descent angle
of 46.56 degrees.
Distance is
velocity squared, sine,
gravity squared.
Sine, 32 feet.
And the distance would be
20,530,372 feet...
or 2,990 miles...
or 46.33 degrees.
Okay, so that puts
your landing zone
at 5.0667 degrees north,
77.3333 degrees west.
Which is here.
Right here.
Give or take 20 square miles.
-I like her numbers.
-(chuckling)
Thank you.
That, of course,
is assuming the capsule hits
the reentry point exactly.
How do we ensure that?
Well, that's the math
we don't have yet, gentlemen.
We're working on it.
Katherine.
What's it gonna take to make
this thing worth the price tag?
Well, we're just getting up
to speed here, Mr. Harrison.
I need more manpower.
I need programmers,
folks to feed the cards.
Get them, for crying out loud.
-Okay.
-All right?
-You're the IBM man, right?
-Yes, sir.
Go pull them out of the sky
if you have to.
Let's get ahead of this
thing or I'm not paying you.
Understood.
I got that one.
I'm not paying any of you!
-Me?
-Temporarily, yes.
We need the IBM
for Glenn's launch.
The lead engineer says
you're good with the cards,
programming and such.
What about the girls here?
Well, human computers can't
calculate an orbital flight
in the time we have.
They'll stay put for now.
What about after now?
(stammering)
After Glenn's launch,
NASA's dissolving
the computing groups.
I'm not accepting
reassignment
unless I bring
my ladies with me.
Excuse me?
We're gonna need a lot of manpower
to program that beast.
I can't do it alone.
My gals are ready.
They can do the work.
DOROTHY:
Ladies.
We've been reassigned.
Leave your calculators.
You won't need them
where we're going.
(up-tempo jazz music playing)
(chattering)
BILL:
Welcome, ladies.
You know what
your job is, Paul?
To find the genius
among those geniuses.
To pull us all up.
We all get to the peak together
or we don't get there at all.
PAUL:
Yes. Well, good night, sir.
I don't know what time
I'm coming home.
Class ends at nine.
You got
something to say?
I thought you might need these.
You can refill them with
any weight lead you want.
You see, you just
hit the top like this.
All right?
The lead comes out.
You put the new lead in...
and new pencil.
You're gonna make
a fine engineer.
You think so?
Yes.
And nobody dare stand
in the way
-of Mary Jackson's dreams.
-(chuckles)
Myself included.
(whispers)
Don't make me mad again.
Yes, ma'am.
And don't make
me late, either.
You gonna be late.
I'm gonna make you late.
-(chuckles)
-You won't be late.
All right, gentlemen.
Tonight, we discuss
Planck-Einstein
wavelength relationships.
Yes?
I'm Mary Jackson.
I'm enrolled.
Well, the curriculum is not
designed for teaching a woman.
Well, I imagine it's the same
as teaching a man.
I don't see
a colored section.
Should I just take any seat?
Thank you.
Okay. Uh...
(clears throat)
Planck-Einstein.
KATHERINE:
The problem
is when the capsule moves
from an elliptical orbit
to a parabolic orbit.
There's no mathematical
formula for that.
Because we can calculate
launch and landing,
but without this conversion,
the capsule stays in orbit,
we can't bring it back home.
Maybe we've been thinking
about this all wrong.
PAUL:
How's that?
Maybe it's not
new math at all.
It could be old math.
Something that looks
at the problem numerically,
and not theoretically.
Math is always dependable.
For you it is.
Euler's method.
-Euler's method.
-Yes.
-That's ancient.
-But it works.
It works numerically.
(chalk squeaking)
That's it.
-Let's type it up.
-Okay.
Huh.
(door opens)
Dorothy.
Mrs. Mitchell.
You're working late today.
Seems to always
happen that way.
Yes. Seems to.
(clears throat)
Thank you.
I hear the IBM's
up to full capacity.
You certainly have
a knack for it.
My father taught me a thing
or two about mechanics.
You know, I have a few girls
in the East Group
that have an interest
in learning more about it.
It is the future.
I may bring them by,
if it's all the same to you.
That's not my decision,
ma'am.
That would be
the supervisor.
Yes, that's true.
Well, good night,
Mrs. Mitchell.
You know, Dorothy.
Despite what you may think...
I have nothing
against y'all.
I know.
I know you
probably believe that.
DOROTHY:
Good night, Katherine.
Good night.
-Mama!
-Hey, babies.
-Mama.
-Hi.
Hey.
Oh, please don't tell me
I missed someone's birthday.
-No, you didn't.
-No, you didn't, Mama.
Madame, your seat.
Well, thank you. (chuckles)
What? Wait.
Is it my birthday?
ALL:
No, Mama.
KATHERINE:
You all look so pretty.
(chuckles)
Mama, what's going on?
Good evening, Katherine.
So you're not gonna say
anything?
It's not my place.
You, either?
Okay. Well, I'm not
gonna do this all night.
(Katherine gasps)
(whispers)
Oh, mother of mercy.
That's for me.
-Are you sad, Mama?
-No.
-It's okay, Mama.
-He's a good man.
I know. I know.
(voice breaking) I just--
I just can't help it.
He hasn't even
asked you yet.
I know, but he is.
-You are, right?
-If y'all will let me.
-Well, go on.
-She's already crying.
Oh, hush.
This was my mother's ring.
(whispers)
It's beautiful.
She and my father
were married for...
For 52 years.
Figure it's about as lucky
a ring as you can get.
The day I met you,
I called my mother
and I said, "Mom, I met
the woman I want to marry."
What'd she say?
She said, "She must be
something, Jimmy.
-Really something."
-Then what'd you say?
I said, "No.
"She's more than something.
She's everything."
Now...
I planned on this being
more romantic.
I'll make that up
to you real soon.
-It's okay.
-But, uh...
But I know marrying you
includes marrying
your girls as well.
Amen to that.
I do.
(chuckles)
I didn't ask you yet.
Hurry up.
(sobbing)
Oh, my goodness.
Oh!
My babies. Look, girls,
isn't it beautiful?
-Look, Mama.
-I see.
ANNOUNCER:
The Mercury-Atlas space vehicle
which will put John Glenn,
the first American,
into Earth's orbit,
has already undergone
five unmanned flight tests.
NASA has confirmed
that the IBM 790
Data Processing System
has been utilized to confirm
all of the mission's
launch and recovery
system calculations.
The modifications
and equipment installations
-are progressing on schedule.
-Yes, sir.
Right in here.
You wanted
to see me, sir?
Have a seat.
Is there something wrong,
Mr. Harrison?
No, there's nothing wrong.
In fact, our IBM is
churning out numbers
in fractions of the time
any human can.
Present company included.
That's good then.
Yeah, maybe.
The thing is,
the Cape's now insisting
on doing all the backups
down there, on site.
I see.
So we won't be running
backups here.
And truth be told,
we can't keep up
with that IBM anyhow.
Long story short,
we no longer need
a computer in this department.
Progress is
a double-edged sword.
(sighs)
Let's have you report back
to the West Group for now.
We'll see if we can find
another assignment.
Thank you, sir.
Katherine, I'm...
I'm sorry about this.
It's out of my hands,
if you can believe that.
I understand.
(sighs)
Katherine.
We heard you got engaged.
Yes.
That's thoughtful of you.
(gasps)
They're lovely.
Mr. Harrison's idea,
really.
Although I suspect his wife
did the picking out.
Can't imagine he has an eye
for anything but numbers.
Now you have
a great wedding.
You did good work
around here, Katherine.
(inaudible)
-(church bell ringing)
-Hello there. Good to see you.
-Hi, Reverend. How you doing?
-How are you?
KATHERINE:
I don't think I felt a thing
the first time I did this.
I was so nervous.
Mm.
You're just as beautiful
as you were back then.
-You think so?
-Mmm.
-Just a little older.
-(gasps)
-And a little fuller.
-(Dorothy laughs)
But you look good.
(sighs)
Well, here we go.
-Again.
-(laughter)
Project Mercury,
named after
the winged messenger of the gods
in Roman mythology.
Today, three years, two months,
and three days afterwards,
we're ready,
after 10 scheduled attempts...
Attagirl.
...to try again to put
our first man into orbit,
to put Colonel John Glenn
into orbit.
Colonel John Glenn will be
the first American
to orbit the Earth.
As you can see, there are
thousands of people here today
to witness this historic event.
Paul, something's off here.
These landing coordinates
don't match yesterday's.
The IBM just ran them.
So, then the IBM was
wrong yesterday. Right?
Or the damn thing's
wrong today.
Paul, am I right?
It appears so.
HARRISON (over phone):
The IBM's been spot-on
up to this point, John.
But we'll run it again,
see what it comes up with.
Look, I'm gonna be honest
with you, Al.
When I fly, I fly the machine.
And right now it seems like
this machine is flying me.
We're on the same page, John.
Our guys are on it.
Let's get the girl
to check the numbers.
-The girl?
-Yes, sir.
You mean Katherine?
Yes, sir. The smart one.
I mean, she says they're
good, I'm ready to go.
All right.
We'll get into it.
GLENN:
Roger.
Sam.
Go find Katherine Goble.
She needs to verify
Glenn's go-no-go
or we're staying
on the ground.
Yes, sir.
(jazzy melody playing)
♪ Whoo! ♪
(panting)
I'm looking
for Katherine Goble.
It's Katherine Johnson now.
They need you to verify
these coordinates.
REPORTER (on TV):
...and tourists have poured
into Cocoa Beach for weeks.
Took this whole area
surrounding Cape Canaveral
and Florida, really.
And all around the country,
it's as if time...
All right, give her
some space. Let her work.
REPORTER: ...as we await
Colonel John Glenn's launch.
A truly historic day
for America.
The country has waited
for several months,
through many failed unmanned
Atlas rocket tests
and 10 scheduled
manned attempts,
which were canceled
for various mechanical
or system complications.
REPORTER 2: All the final tests
and checks are being conducted.
John Glenn is ready to board
the Friendship 7.
REPORTER 1: But today
we remain truly optimistic,
and it's a go day
in all regards.
The capsule is ready.
The rocket itself is A-Okay,
and the weather here
at Cape Canaveral...
-Anything from Langley?
-Not yet.
REPORTER 1: We are being told
that Mission Control at NASA
is conducting a final check
of the launch
and recovery coordinates,
including the go-no-go
calculations so crucial
to a safe and successful
launch and recovery.
REPORTER 2:
After years of waiting,
and months of delay,
Colonel Glenn is finally ready
for that space flight
that we've been waiting for
with so much anticipation.
REPORTER 1: These last-minute
checks could indicate
a hesitancy
on NASA's behalf.
But let us say,
without reservation,
that the safety
of Colonel John Glenn
is paramount to the mission
and to the nation itself.
No, sir.
We're still a go.
Yes, sir.
(muttering indistinctly)
That's it.
(sighs)
What the devil are you doing?
Are you taking a break?
(gospel music playing)
♪ Yes! ♪
♪ Say, yeah ♪
♪ Yeah ♪
♪ Say, yeah! ♪
♪ Don't you know
that we're able ♪
♪ And that alone
makes us major ♪
♪ Yes, we can ♪
♪ Yours and my alchemy ♪
♪ Are one and one
equals three ♪
♪ Yes, we can ♪
♪ I feel it like lightning
in the forest ♪
♪ Yes, we can ♪
♪ Pick an order, pick a note
and harmonize the chorus ♪
♪ You're my woman
don't need another ♪
♪ Get behind me, under
we can lift each other ♪
♪ Tornado weather
we another level ♪
♪ Whoo! ♪
-Do you have the time?
-♪ Yeah ♪
♪ Yes, we can ♪
♪ Like a solar system
that's surrounded by you ♪
♪ Yes, we can ♪
♪ Pick an order, pick a note
and harmonize the chorus ♪
♪ You're my woman
don't need another ♪
♪ Get behind, under
we can lift each other ♪
♪ Tornado weather
we another level ♪
♪ Whoo! ♪
♪ You're my woman
don't need another ♪
♪ Get behind me, under
we can lift each other ♪
♪ Tornado weather
we another level ♪
-♪ Whoo! ♪
-(door slams)
Sir.
(telephone ringing)
Pad 14.
Katherine.
Come on.
Sir, we've got
Pad 14 on the box.
HARRISON: All right.
Let me in there.
HARRISON:
This is Langley,
we have
the coordinates confirmed.
MAN (over speakers):
Stand by, Langley.
HARRISON:
We can confirm
the go-no-go point
for reentry is
16.11984 degrees latitude,
-165.2356 degrees longitude.
The launch window is a go.
The landing coordinates match.
That is very good news, Al.
It's a little hard to trust
something
you can't look in the eyes.
That's right, Colonel.
Katherine did manage
to calculate
a few decimal points further
than that hunk of metal.
GLENN (over speakers):
I will take every digit you got.
Be sure to thank her for me.
Gentlemen,
let's launch this rocket.
Good luck, Friendship 7.
Godspeed, Langley.
REPORTER:
Here at Cape Canaveral
the countdown has resumed
as Colonel John Glenn is
now aboard the Friendship 7
high above
the Atlas rocket on Pad 14,
a height of over 93 feet.
So far, the countdown is...
REPORTER 2: These are pictures
from Cape Canaveral, Florida.
The gantry is now moving back.
And we are a go for launch.
MAN (on TV): The Mercury
spacecraft umbilical is out.
T-minus 10 seconds
and counting.
Water systems, go.
-Mercury capsule, go.
-...eight, seven,
-six, five...
-Ready engine. Start.
...four...
-three, two...
-Good Lord, ride all the way.
(over radio)
...one, zero.
Ignition.
Liftoff.
The M-A 6 vehicle
has lifted off.
It's getting
a little bumpy along here.
Roger that.
You are in Max Q.
GLENN:
Roger that, CAPCOM.
CAPCOM:
All systems are reported go.
20 seconds to SECO.
The trajectory is still A-Okay.
Go for SECO.
GLENN:
Roger that, CAPCOM.
Go for SECO.
Zero G and I feel fine.
REPORTER: John Glenn reports
everything looks good.
Oh, that view is tremendous!
Roger that, Friendship 7.
You are go for orbit.
Thank you, CAPCOM.
All right.
Ten and a half hours to go.
If we make seven round-trips.
I could use a coffee.
TV REPORTER:
Well, as we approach
the end of the day here
on the Eastern Seaboard,
Colonel Glenn is just
beginning his third orbit
three-quarters of the way across
the African continent.
We see he's
currently over Zanzibar
which is the next tracking
station coming up.
-Thankfully, the Friendship 7 capsule...
-(turns off broadcast)
New assignment
came down the pike.
Always changing
around here.
It's hard to keep up.
Seems like they're going
to need a permanent team
to feed that IBM.
How big of a team?
Thirty, to start.
Thank you for the information,
Mrs. Mitchell.
You're quite welcome,
Mrs. Vaughan.
Hmm.
We have a warning light.
CAPCOM 7,
I have a warning light.
Stand by, Seven.
Sir, we have a warning light.
What are we looking at, Paul?
The, uh...
The heat shield
may have come loose.
Seven, will you confirm
the landing bag
is in the off position?
Affirmative, CAPCOM.
Al, we need to get him down now.
He could burn up on reentry.
Come on, babies.
There is a man in space,
and we don't want to miss it,
so we gotta hurry.
MAN: Something's
wrong with Glenn!
-What's going on?
-Come on, let's go.
-Come on. Hurry up, now.
-MARY: Y'all follow me.
We just learned
that the Friendship 7
is in danger of losing
its heat shield.
Have you heard
any banging noises
or anything of this type
at higher rates?
That is a negative, CAPCOM.
This poses a grave danger
to the mission.
Tell them not to jettison
the retro-package.
MAN (on radio):
NASA is confirming
there is some sort
of malfunction
with the capsule's heat shield
and it may not stay in place.
If the heat shield's loose,
the retro-package straps
might... might hold it in place.
-Will that work?
-It will work.
It will hold it until he reaches
the go-no-go point.
It will work.
Al, he has
to override the .05G.
Do it.
Friendship 7,
we're recommending
that the retro-package not--
I repeat, not be jettisoned.
(over radio): This means that
you will have to override the .05G switch.
Roger.
Is there a reason
for this? Over.
Stand by, Seven.
Not at this time, Seven.
Roger that, Command.
I will make a manual
.05G entry
and bring the scope in. Over.
He knows.
REPORTER (over radio):
Without a heat shield,
there is no way that
Colonel Glenn can get back
through the Earth's
atmosphere.
The heat is simply
too overpowering.
A malfunction in
the automatic control system
is causing the spacecraft to yaw
in a skid-like fashion.
Thus putting the Friendship 7's
reentry point in jeopardy.
Even now, Colonel Glenn is streaking
towards the United States,
and he must begin the retro-sequence
300 miles west of California
if he's to reenter the atmosphere
at the designated point
and land in the recovery area
700 miles south and east of Florida.
Stay tuned to this station
for further details.
You're going to be using
fly-by-wire for reentry.
You'll need to maintain
a zero angle, over.
Roger. I'm on fly-by-wire.
Back it up with manual. Over.
Keep talking to him.
Roger. The weather,
the recovery area
three-foot waves,
10 miles visibility.
-(distorted speech over radio)
-CAPCOM, you're going out.
He's crossing
the communication blackout zone.
There's a real fireball outside.
It's getting
a little hot in here.
(distorted speech over radio)
(distorted speech continues)
CAPCOM, do you copy?
(static crackling)
Friendship 7, do you copy? Over.
Again.
Friendship 7,
do you copy? Over.
-Loud and clear, CAPCOM.
-(excited chattering)
Roger that.
How are you doing?
My condition is good.
That was a real fireball. Boy!
Roger that.
Let's get you
all the way home.
GLENN (over speakers):
Roger that.
Here's hoping these landing
coordinates still hold.
-Approaching 16.11984.
-Roger.
Approaching minus 165.2356...
in three, two, one.
Engaging chutes.
Beautiful chute!
How are we looking, CAPCOM?
CAPCOM:
Your go-no-go is good.
Landing coordinates
are spot-on, Seven.
GLENN:
Roger that, CAPCOM.
I've always wanted to swim
in the Bahamas. Over.
(cheering)
John Glenn has splashed down
and he is being recovered.
-Thank you!
-(cheering)
John Glenn has
splashed down safely
and is being recovered
by the USS Noa.
-Good job.
-Great job, guys.
HARRISON:
Katherine.
Nice work.
You too,
Mr. Harrison.
So, um...
you think
we can get to the Moon?
We're already there, sir.
(chuckles)
Yeah.
-Thank you so much.
-Thank you.
(cheering)
Girls, this is Mrs. Vaughan,
your supervisor.
She'll show you
how things work.
Come on in.
The IBM 7090
Data Processing System
is capable of solving 24,000
multiplications per second.
♪ They'll call it a mystery ♪
♪ But we're gonna
call it victory ♪
♪ We'll be writing history ♪
♪ It's gonna be ♪
♪ Victory ♪
♪ They'll be signs
on top of signs ♪
♪ Just so you know the ♪
♪ History ♪
♪ It's saying victory ♪
♪ Is with me ♪
♪ Oh, let them laugh about it ♪
♪ Don't worry
what the doubter's saying ♪
♪ Yes, it's an uphill battle ♪
♪ But guess
who else is playin' ♪
♪ The next time
y'all in action ♪
♪ And the Ghost is
in the room ♪
♪ Watch you work
through the masses ♪
♪ You know
that we've been used ♪
-♪ Let go, let it be ♪
-♪ No matter how deep ♪
-♪ I swear just believe ♪
♪ You'll find victory ♪
♪ Find your victory ♪
♪ They'll call it a mystery ♪
♪ But we're gonna call it ♪
♪ Victory ♪
♪ We'll be writing history ♪
♪ It's gonna be ♪
♪ Victory ♪
♪ They'll be signs
on top of signs ♪
♪ Just so you know the ♪
♪ History ♪
♪ It's saying victory ♪
♪ Is with me ♪
♪ The Bible says
you should pray for nothing ♪
♪ 'Cause every week
it's gonna be something ♪
♪ You know the devil
can't wait to jump in ♪
♪ And complicate
the things you trust in ♪
♪ But I know my foundation ♪
♪ Is solid and can take
some hating ♪
♪ Prayer's gon' be
on this space station ♪
♪ On the way
to the master's apron ♪
♪ They'll call it a mystery ♪
♪ Victory ♪
♪ We'll be writing history ♪
♪ It's gon' be ♪
♪ Victory ♪
♪ It's saying victory ♪
♪ Is with me ♪
(upbeat music playing)
♪ Hey! ♪
♪ Oh ♪
(vocalizing)
♪ When I first got here ♪
♪ Tried to find my way ♪
♪ For the end of the days
were dark ♪
♪ When I was not clear ♪
♪ You showed me
my mistakes ♪
♪ But told me keep the pace
don't get lost ♪
♪ So I shall not fear, yeah ♪
♪ That's how it feels
when you love me ♪
♪ And you're my sightseer ♪
♪ 'Cause before
I'm in a rut ♪
♪ You multiply by 10 times
what they took from me ♪
♪ Hey ♪
♪ You send out a branch
from the longest tree ♪
♪ When I'm in quicksand ♪
♪ But in my mind
it's really your arm to me ♪
♪ Can't believe it, what a lift
and hard to believe ♪
♪ Surrender ♪
♪ But there's a difference ♪
-♪ Surrender ♪
♪ Surrender ♪
♪ 'Cause I understand
explain to me ♪
♪ There's no coincidence ♪
♪ Just confirmation ♪
♪ Let me see them hands ♪
♪ I was down on myself ♪
♪ And I called you ♪
♪ And your answer is
"What can I do?" ♪
♪ So much you do for me ♪
♪ In the sound of my breath
seen all the years ♪
♪ Of surrender ♪
♪ Just know I'm here ♪
♪ Reporting for duty ♪
♪ When it feel this good
don't ever let go, go ♪
♪ Don't ever let go, oh ♪
♪ When it feel this good
don't ever let go, go ♪
-♪ Don't ever let go, oh ♪
♪ Hard to believe ♪
♪ Surrender ♪
♪ But there's a difference ♪
-♪ Surrender ♪
♪ 'Cause I understand
explain to me ♪
♪ There's no coincidence ♪
♪ Just confirmation ♪
♪ Let me see them hands ♪
♪ Please, just wave ♪
♪ Wave, wave ♪
♪ Wave, wave, wave ♪
♪ In this place ♪
♪ Just wave, wave ♪
♪ Wave your hands ♪
-♪ Wave ♪
♪ Wave ♪
(hip-hop music playing)
♪ Trying understand the way
I've been behaving ♪
♪ It's a funny thing
you really gotta see ♪
♪ Is it just your love
that's got me going crazy? ♪
♪ Or are my eyes
playing with me ♪
♪ Heat, heat ♪
♪ All day your love
just comes shining down ♪
♪ Heat, heat ♪
♪ Just like
the sweat just beats ♪
♪ Heat, heat ♪
♪ I feel you from my root
to my crown ♪
♪ Heat, heat ♪
-♪ Just like the kundalini ♪
-♪ Kundalini ♪
♪ From the caramel,
he's right beside me ♪
♪ My mind's his carousel ♪
♪ That's how he rides me ♪
-♪ So there's no parallels ♪
-♪ A place to hide me ♪
♪ Y'all know me very well ♪
♪ It's yellow lightning ♪
♪ Trying to understand the way
I've been behaving ♪
♪ It's a funny thing
you really gotta see ♪
♪ Is it just your love
that's got me going crazy ♪
♪ Or are my eyes
playing with me ♪
♪ Just like a mirage ♪
♪ I love you
like you were gold ♪
♪ Just like a mirage ♪
♪ I love you
like you were gold ♪
♪ Just like a mirage ♪
♪ I love you
like you were gold ♪
♪ Gold, gold ♪
♪ And I'm sorry, baby ♪
♪ For the what ifs, maybes ♪
♪ I take it too far ♪
♪ I know I must be
looking crazy ♪
♪ I'm sorry, baby ♪
♪ For the what ifs, maybes ♪
♪ I take it too far ♪
♪ You know I must be
looking crazy ♪
♪ Trying to understand the way
I've been behaving ♪
♪ It's a funny thing
you really gotta see ♪
♪ Is it just your love
that's got me going crazy ♪
♪ Or are my eyes
playing with me ♪
♪ I spent many nights
on my knees praying ♪
♪ From the side effects
of all this heat ♪
♪ But I'm telling y'all
it does feel amazing ♪
♪ Or are my eyes
playing with me ♪